Daniele Foroni | Ph.D.

My research interests focus on Big Data Management and Analysis, particularly on the assessment of the quality of the data and to analysis considering sport data. During my PhD, I studied how to improve the quality of the data by considering the involved application and the optimization metric the user has in mind, as well as the intrinsic value of the data. To do so, I built F4U, a framework for measuring the impact of some noise on the accuracy of the results, and Moira, a system to dynamically allocate the right amount of resource to optimize the goal metric defined by the user.

Current position

From 2019 **Big Data Senior Research Engineer**, *Huawei ERC (European Research Center)*, Munich, Germany.

August Research and develop Big Data technologies with special focus on real-time and streaming technologies, and techniques for traffic management optimization in smart city environments.

Education

2014–2019 **PhD in Computer Science**, *University of Trento*, Italy.

Thesis: Putting Data Quality in Context: How to generate more accurate analyses.

Advisor: Yannis Velegrakis

2012–2014 **Master of Science in Computer Science**, *University of Trento*, Italy, 102/110.

2009–2012 **Bachelor of Science in Computer Science**, *University of Trento*, Italy, 97/110.

Work Experience

2018 Oct- CTO and Developer, IOHub, Rovereto, Italy.

Present Development of technologies and solutions for financial invoices for Italian businesses and citizens, providing an integration with the ad-hoc system created by the Italian Revenue Agency.

2017–2018 **PhD Intern**, *Huawei ERC*, Munich, Germany.

Visiting researcher working on dynamic rescheduling resources for streaming queries in a distributed environment based on the goal metric defined by the user.

Advisors: Stefano Bortoli and Radu Tudoran

2016–2017 **Data Scientist**, *University of Trento and Saidea SRL*, Trento, Italy.

Development of XplainBox, an industrial project that from a stream of data, stores it, and then analyzes and applies

ML algorithms on it.

2014 **Intern Data Engineer**, *Engineering Tributi SPA*, Trento, Italy.

Feb-Nov Development of a tool for resolving similar entities in a dataset obtained integrating multiple sources from the public administrative domain. Given a set of rules, the proposed solution builds a lattice of operations that efficiently and offsetively finds similar entities without running soveral algorithms over the whole dataset.

effectively finds similar entities without running several algorithms over the whole dataset.

Advisor: Nicola Mezzetti

Teaching Experience

2015–2019 TA, Big Data and Social Networks, *University of Trento*, Trento, Italy.

Computer Science and Data Science Master course about big data technologies that covers from the storage of such an amount of data (NoSQL, HDFS) to its analysis (Hadoop MapReduce, Spark, ML models, Streaming, Graph processing).

Professor: Yannis Velegrakis

2017 **Big Data Technologies**, *TIM*, Trento, Italy.

On site and from remote course about Big Data Technologies for scientists working in TIM. The program covered from the storage of such an amount of data (NoSQL, HDFS) to its analysis (Hadoop MapReduce, Spark, ML models, Streaming, Graph processing).

2015–2016 **TA, Programming for Mathematicians**, *University of Trento*, Trento, Italy.

Bachelor course for introducing Math students to programming.

Professor: Roberto Zunino

Skills

Programming	Python .	Iava - Scala	· C# · SOL ·	Iavascript
i rogramming	I y ti tori	java Scara	CII OQL	javascript

Apache Spark · Flink · Kafka · Hadoop · NoSQL Framework

Scalable Machine Learning with Apache Spark Certifications

OS & Tools Linux · Bash · Git

> Machine Learning · Data Mining ΑI

Publications

Putting Data Quality in Context 2019 Under review in TKDE

D. Foroni, M. Lissandrini, and Y. Velegrakis

F4U: The Contextualized Data Quality System Under review in VLDB 2019

D. Foroni, M. Lissandrini, and Y. Velegrakis

On Contextualizing Data Quality 2019 Submitted to Sigmod Record

D. Foroni, M. Lissandrini, and Y. Velegrakis

Moira: A Goal-Oriented Incremental Machine Learning Approach to Dynamic Resource 2018 BIRTE '19 doi:10.1145/3242153.3242160 Cost Estimation in Distributed Stream Processing Systems

D. Foroni, C. Axenie, S. Bortoli, M. Al Hajj Hassan, R. Acker, R. Tudoran, G. Brasche, and Y. Velegrakis

STARLORD: Sliding Window Temporal Accumulate-Retract Learning for Online ICMLA '18 doi:10.1109/ICMLA.2018.00181 Reasoning on Datastreams

C. Axenie, R. Tudoran, S. Bortoli, M. Al Hajj Hassan, D. Foroni, and G. Brasche

2018 Data Management and Smart Cities

UniTN - White Paper '18 M. Brugnara, C. Consonni, **D. Foroni**, S. Pasupathipillai, G. Preti, P. Sottovia, and Y. Velegrakis Trento - Smart Cities

Projects

Exploit data information for Entity Matching, Ongoing work. 2019

Exploit the intrinsic value of the data through a profile to improve the accuracy of the duplicates found.

Data Quality Measurement, Ongoing work. 2017

Providing the user an estimation of the quality of a dataset for a specific application.

2017 Creation of analysis from a data lake with Data Mining and ML algorithms, and statistics, Industrial

work.

Designed a flow from the reading of the data to the analysis, which is performed with Data Mining and Machine Learning algorithms to provide the user the key insights from the available data.

Other activities

SEA Data 2020 PC member

CSGRID · EDBT · JPDC · ICMLA · VLDB · KDD - SIGMOD Record Reviewer

Languages

Full professional proficiency (C1) English

Basic knowledge (A1) German

Native Italian